If you struggle with a lack
of self-confidence, you need to hear this.
I feel like everyone at some point in their lives do
deal with some sort of lack of self-confidence or lack of self-esteem,
and that can cause a big hindrance on
not only your relationship with your friends, but partners,
as well as just networking
in general if you're not self-confident.
Self-confidence does come naturally to some, but for most people,
it has to be attained and developed like any other skill.
And before you can actually
start working on your actual confidence,
you have to find out where the root of the problem is
and find out where the lack of self-confidence is actually coming from.
Hold on, hold on, hold on.
Before we hop into all the juicy stuff
and everything we're going to talk about today,
please, if you can, leave us a like and subscribe.
We'd really appreciate it.
Some great content coming in the future.
Let's get into it.
So what actually leads to a lack of self-confidence?
And before we actually get into these points,
something that you need to do while we're having this conversation
is you really need to look at yourself in the mirror
and really find out what
the root of the problem is.
And you need to really open up your heart
and your mind and be open-minded to be like,
okay, what's actually going on and
why am I feeling this way, right?
So at the beginning, it's going to be surface level.
And these are things like your appearance.
Are you comfortable with your own skin, the
way you look, your haircuts, stuff like that?
Two, your physical shape.
Like, are you comfortable with, you know, maybe you
want to lose weight, maybe you want to gain weight.
Maybe you feel like you have skinny
arms and you want to have bigger arms.
That was actually an insecurity that I
had growing up was I was always super,
skinny, had a fast metabolism and was never
really able to put on the weight, right?
But I'll be talking about how
I conquered that later on the video.
Next one, this is a little bit deeper, is what
are your peers and your family environment saying and influencing you?
Maybe you're going down a different path than your
siblings or family members expect you to go to,
or you want to pursue a different dream that's
different than what they had originally envisioned for you.
And that is playing a role on your mental.
Or maybe your friends aren't really being supportive of you.
And your dreams and goals and ambitions
and just what you're doing right now.
That's another thing.
But now to get into really a little bit deeper stuff
and stuff that can really fuck up people's mental for being honest.
And that's stuff like your bad breakup
or bad academic and work performance, poor finances.
Maybe you're living paycheck to paycheck.
You're not sure how you're going to
put food on the table next week.
That's a big one.
Your overall mindset and positive thinking.
Are you practicing gratitude?
Things like that.
So everything we just talked about
and listed off are all things.
That can lead to a lack of self-confidence.
But the things right now that we're going to talk about are some of
the signs where you can kind of point out in your day to day.
Like, hey, maybe I'm lacking some self-confidence here.
Right.
And one of those is
thinking people are better than you.
And that's a big one.
And something that I struggled with growing up as well is not really being
confident in your own abilities to accomplish a job, task, subject, whatever it may be.
Because you think, oh, I'll
never be as good as Janet.
I'll never be as good as James
because, you know, there's so much more.
I'm not going to be as good as my parents.
And yes, you know what?
Maybe they are better than you
at the current time and place.
But that doesn't mean that you
cannot get to that same point.
And the reason I say that is because everyone is capable of doing anything you
want to do as long as you put the time in and the work in.
So no one is truly better than you.
You can really accomplish anything.
Two is being too self-critical.
There is a fine line with this.
And the reason being is because when it
comes to self-improvement, being critical of yourself is important.
But to a certain degree.
Analyzing what you're doing wrong throughout the day or what
you're doing wrong on an activity is a good practice.
But being self-critical to the point where you are
just critical, like you're just being in critical condition.
You can't move forward because
you're like, I'm not good enough.
This isn't good enough.
And it's just bullshit.
Like you just have to realize that, hey,
when you do something good enough is perfect.
For 99% of things, good enough is perfect.
Number three, we have not
taking note of your accomplishments.
And this is a big one.
Like if you win a competition and maybe you do something really cool or
you did something outstanding in the workplace, like you should be proud of that.
You really should be, you know, own up to it, you know,
treat yourself to something nice because what you did is actually awesome.
But if you're not actually taking note of that and realizing that, hey, I did something good, like you really do need to practice some gratitude and
be thankful for, hey, not only did I do a great job, other people are appreciating that I did a good job and I actually won something.
Next one's a big one.
And it's really just not.
Not keeping up with your appearance,
at least for the bare essentials.
Right.
And really from a guy's perspective, like just basic grooming, you know, like cutting your nails, wearing deodorant, you know, trying to smell a little bit good and trimming your beard,
you know, getting a haircut every once in a while or whatever your hairstyle, you know, needs to at least, you know, look good and really just basic grooming, you know.
And the reason being is because oftentimes if I was to go out and let's
say, you know, maybe I haven't cut my nails or I forgot to put deodorant on.
I don't feel comfortable in my own skin.
So imagine like I give off a different
energy and I don't come off nearly as confident.
And it's really just something to consider is at least
be doing the bare minimum to keep up with your appearance.
And I feel like this one right
here is a real hidden killer of self-confidence.
And that is just not
having plans for anything at all.
And the reason I say this is because oftentimes when I talk to people
and they don't have confidence is because they feel like they have no control.
Over their lives and really the I think the best way to go about really fixing this is just by setting up a goal or dream finding something that
you really want to work to and then create a plan and an accomplishable steps to actually achieve that because you really need to feel in control of your life.
If you want to have a sense of confidence.
Now that we've talked about, you know, what are some of the
things that lead to a lack of self-confidence and some of the signs?
Well, how do you actually bounce back?
And so one of the
first things that you can do.
Is to stop comparing yourself to others like just cut it out and really just focus on you and
the people that actually support you and because when you compare yourself to others people everyone has their own destination.
Everyone has their own timeline
and everyone is so different.
Your time is coming and you really I think
I'm social media is a big contributor to this.
Like if you feel like people's, you know, maybe some of their tweets are bringing you down or
like you keep comparing yourself to the Kardashians, whatever just hit that on a follow button, you know, stop.
Stop.
Stop putting that image in that picture in your mind.
Just cut it out and just focus on you.
The next thing is really you have to understand that
you can only control yourself your actions and your decisions.
The people around you and the events that
happen to you are out of your control.
You cannot control your brother's decisions.
You can't control your roommates decisions.
You can control your family's decisions and you sure as hell
can't control the decision of some random guy on the street, right?
All you can focus on and control is what?
Your decisions are so you
really just need to encompass that.
Hey, all I can dictate is my personal life.
So I'm going to make the decisions that work out best for
me and it's going to make me a better version of me.
This third one is a big one and it's really on touching on a point that we talked about earlier and that's just creating an environment of support and positivity
for yourself because this is such a big role, especially on your mindset and just mental in general is because if you're around people who do nothing but bring you down.
Bring you down call it, you know, your little dream or the little thing that you're trying
to accomplish or they're not supportive of you and uplifting you and encouraging you to keep going.
You need to cut them off.
That's family.
That's friends.
That's just random people around you.
You just need to get out of there.
Like seriously, you need to cut them off.
Even if they're old friends, you need
to cut them off because trust me.
There's so many people in the world that are going to that would be willing to
support you and be positive uplift you and even give you ideas that better what you're doing.
That there's no time for people
that are just going to be toxic.
Just cut them off.
So now that we're on the balance back, how
do we establish general self-confidence in everything that we do?
So after you've had that conversation with yourself and you've recognized the flaws and
the things you actually want to improve on it's time to create a plan.
And that's really the step one of part.
All of this is creating a plan to improve
on the flaws that you have within your life.
So you really want to do this by setting up a bigger
vision and setting up the actual end result that you want to achieve.
Whether that's a certain financial, you know, goal that you want to get to or you
want to look a certain way appearance-wise, you have a fitness goal, whatever it may be.
Right after you set up the final destination.
It's time to set achievable and bite-sized goals that you can set along the way
and actually track your progress and see the hey, I'm going on the right way.
You know, I'm doing I'm doing the things that I need to
be doing in order to get to where I want to be.
Right?
But something you have to understand throughout all of
this is that even though you have a plan.
And of where you want
to be, it's okay to fail.
Like you are going to fail throughout these processes.
Why you're learning to be the best version of yourself.
Like it is okay to fail.
And that's just one of the things you
have to understand it and really adopt within yourself.
It's really just having a growth mindset that
like, hey, there's going to be ups and downs.
But at the end of this, I'm going to be the best
version of myself and I'm going to be unrecognizable to the old me.
Another thing that you really have to understand when
it comes to confidence is that a lot of it.
Is really through experience.
So if I was a set up, you
know sign up for a sales job tomorrow, right?
If I was going to be selling decks and patios that first appointment
that I go to even though I've gone through the training and everything.
I'm not going to be super confident.
I mean, yeah, maybe I believe in the product and I believe in myself, but
I will be nowhere near as confident as I would be on my 500th appointment.
And the reason being is just because experience
is a big factor when it comes to confidence.
So it's perfectly normal to be uncomfortable
and nervous when you're trying something new.
But just recognize the hey, I will never get to where I want to be unless I actually try to try
things succeed at some and also fail at some but ultimately experience does have a big factor when it comes to self-confidence.
So to sum up this video very shortly.
It's really two things is first is to identify the problem
and see where the lack of confidence is actually really coming from.
And the second one is to assess the situation cut off anything that's actually, you know, the toxic friends the family, whatever it may be get them out and
then create an actionable plan to actually get to where you want to be in terms of your self-confidence and really what you want to be and look like.